A Guide to the John H. Knowles Papers FA047
Rockefeller Archive Center
- The Rockefeller Foundation, 1961-1980; 4; 10 Cubic Feet
  - The Rockefeller Foundation - Manuscripts, D
    - "Montreal Neurological Institute and the Rockefeller Foundation: The Lengthened Shadows on Penfield and Gregg", 1978 (Box 100, Folder 1155)
    - "Neo-Liberalism", 1976 (Box 100, Folder 1156)
    - "New Bellevue Hospital Center", 1973 (Box 100, Folder 1157)
    - "New Directions in Health Care in the State of Colorado", 1978 (Box 100, Folder 1158)
    - "New School for Social Research", 1973 (Box 100, Folder 1159)
    - New York University Medical Center Commencement Talk, 1973 (Box 100, Folder 1160)
    - "On Doing More with Less", 1975-1976 (Box 100, Folder 1161)
    - "Perspectives on American Health", 1977 (Box 100, Folder 1162)
    - "Perspectives on the National Health Issue", 1978 (Box 100, Folder 1163)
    - Pratt Institute Commencement Talk, 1973 (Box 100, Folder 1164)
    - "Public Policy on Abortion", 1974 (Box 100, Folder 1165)
    - "Rational for Increased United States Interest in International Health", 1977 (Box 100, Folder 1166)
    - "Reaching 800 Million Small Cars" (Box 101, Folder 1167)
    - "Reflections on Who's in Charge and Why", 1974 (Box 101, Folder 1168)
    - "Religion and the University", 1977 (Box 101, Folder 1169)
    - "Responsibility for Health", 1977 (Box 101, Folder 1170)
    - "Responsiblity of the Individual", 1977 (Box 101, Folder 1171)
    - "Role of Foundations", 1978 (Box 101, Folder 1172)
    - "Roles of the University in the Post-Colonial World", 1975 (Box 101, Folder 1173)
    - Schmitt Medal Presentation Talk, 1973 (Box 101, Folder 1174)
    - "Scarcity, Global Interdependence and Ethnicity", 1974 (Box 101, Folder 1175)
    - "Secure Freedom", 1973 (Box 101, Folder 1176)
    - "Some Observations on America's Health Delivery System", 1974 (Box 101, Folder 1177)
    - "Spellbinding and Spellbreaking in American Medicine", 1974 (Box 101, Folder 1178)
    - Statement Before Senate Finance Committee - Subcommittee on Foundations, 1974 (Box 101, Folder 1179)
    - "Struggle to Stay Healthy", 1975-1976 (Box 101, Folder 1180)
    - "Thoughts on Health, Population and Development", 1978 (Box 101, Folder 1181)
    - Unidentified (Box 101, Folder 1182)
    - United Hospital Fund Campaign Talk, 1972 (Box 101, Folder 1183)
    - "United States Policy and World Health", 1974 (Box 101, Folder 1184)
    - "Unseen Ostrich in Our Teaching Hospitals", 1973 (Box 101, Folder 1185)
    - "Utopia or Dystopia in an Age of Confusion", 1972-1973 (Box 101, Folder 1186)
    - "Virtues and Values in American Life", Address at the University of Pennsylvania Commencement and University of Maine Commencement, 1972, 1975, 1978 (Box 101, Folder 1187)
    - "Volunteerism and Plurialism in American Life", 1974 (Box 101, Folder 1188)
    - 'Watershed' Book, 1973 (Box 102, Folder 1189)
    - "What Keeps Men Together", 1978 (Box 102, Folder 1190)
    - Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology, 1974 (Box 102, Folder 1191)
    - "World of Health and the American Physician", 1973 (Box 102, Folder 1192)
  - The Rockefeller Foundation - Printed Material, E
    Subseries E consists of three folders of printed material including articles about and interviews with Dr. Knowles.
    - Articles about Knowles, 1976-1979 (Box 102, Folder 1193)
    - Articles about Knowles, 1971-1975 (Box 102, Folder 1194)
    - Interviews, 1972-1974 (Box 102, Folder 1195)
  - The Rockefeller Foundation - Information Files, F
    Subseries F consists of one folder of information files that Dr. Knowles kept for reference purposes.
    - General (Box 102, Folder 1196)
- Miscellaneous, 1959-1979; 5; 12 Cubic Feet
  This series contains odd sized items, including weekly appointment cards (1961-1970), appointment calendars (1959-1979), 21 scrapbooks (1962-1972) containing clippings, photographs, letters, and memorabilia; miscellaneous newspaper clippings, certificates and plaques, microscope slides and lantern slides, reel and cassette tapes, and three watercolors of Dr. Knowles and an aerial view of Boston.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (audio tape, film) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
  Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services / Head of Reference.
  - Clippings - Massachusetts General Hospital, 1964-1965 (Box 102, Folder 1197)
  - Clippings - Rockefeller Foundation, 1971-1972 (Box 102, Folder 1198)
  - Clippings - Rockefeller Foundation, 1973-1975, n.d. (Box 103, Folder 1199)
  - Clippings - Labor, 1965 (Box 103, Folder 1200)
  - Clippings - American Medical Association, 1972 (Box 103, Folder 1201)
  - Clippings - Boston City Hospital (Box 103, Folder 1202)
  - Clippings - Boston City Hospital (Box 103, Folder 1203)
  - Clippings - John H. Knowles Obituary, 1979 (Box 103, Folder 1204)
  - Weekly Appointment Cards, 1961-1968 (Box 104, Folder 1205)
  - Weekly Appointment Cards, 1969-1970 (Box 105, Folder 1206)
  - Appointment Calendars, 1959-1979 (Box 106, Folder 1207)
  - Cash Book, 1959 (Box 106, Folder 1208)
  - Guest Book (Box 106, Folder 1209)
  - Scrapbooks, February 1962-June 1972 (Box 107, Folder 1210)
  - Scrapbooks, February 1962-June 1972 (Box 108, Folder 1211)
  - Scrapbooks, February 1962-June 1972 (Box 109, Folder 1212)
  - Scrapbooks, February 1962-June 1972 (Box 110, Folder 1213)
  - Nixon Lodge Spots (Box 111, Folder 1214)
    Reel-to-Reel Audio Tape.
  - "Outlook" - John H. Knowles with Jack Kelly - W-EZE, January 18, 1970 (Box 111, Folder 1215)
  - Finch, Knowles, Egeberg (Box 111, Folder 1216)
  - Dr. Knowles Lecture, October 28, 1969 (Box 111, Folder 1217)
  - "Conversation Piece" - Haywood Vincent with John H. Knowles, January 22, 1970 (Box 111, Folder 1218)
  - "Issues and Inquiry - Public Medicine: New Prescription for the Nation's Health" - Joseph R. Baylor with John H. Knowles (Box 111, Folder 1219)
  - Address at the New England Sinai Hospital Development Fund Dinner, Octoer 26, 1969 (Box 111, Folder 1220)
    Cassette Tape.
  - "The Watershed of the Seventies" - Ward Darley Seminar - University of Colorado Medical Center, January 4, 1971 (Box 111, Folder 1221)
    Parts I, II, III; Cassette Tape.
  - "The Watershed of the Seventies" - Ward Darley Seminar - University of Colorado Medical Center, January 4, 1971 (Box 111, Folder 1222)
  - "A Celebration of the Memory and Love of John H. Knowles, 1926-1979", March 16, 1979 (Box 111, Folder 1223)
  - "Health Care and the City" - McGraw-Hill Sound Seminars - Fran P. Hosken and John H. Knowles (Box 111, Folder 1224)
  - "Health Care and the City" - McGraw-Hill Sound Seminars - Fran P. Hosken and John H. Knowles (Box 111, Folder 1225)
  - Regarding Knowles Address at Bellevue Hospital, 1973 (Box 111, Folder 1226)
  - Mt. Sinai Instructions about Hospital to Help John H. Knowles Prepare Talk, September 24, 1974 (Box 111, Folder 1227)
  - J. Knowles - Schistosomaisis - China, 1975 (Box 111, Folder 1228)
  - Hsin Hua Hospital - China, 1972 (Box 111, Folder 1229)
  - Hsin Hua Hospital - China, 1972 (Box 111, Folder 1230)
  - "Open Mind", May 2, 1976 (Box 111, Folder 1231)
  - Mintzberg - American Medical Association (Box 111, Folder 1232)
  - Arlene Francis Program with John H. Knowles - WOR Radio, May 7, 1973 (Box 112, Folder 1233)
  - Dr. Knowles - Duplicate from Louise and Gus, January 1, 1964 (Box 112, Folder 1234)
  - "Health Care and the City" - McGraw-Hill, Sound Seminars - Fran P. Hooken and John H. Knowles (Box 112, Folder 1235)
  - John H. Knowles - NET-TV, June 30, 1969 (Box 112, Folder 1236)
  - John H. Knowles on the Sherrye Henry Program - "A Tale of Two Cities" - WOR (New York) and Capitol Radio (London), November 1, 1978 (Box 112, Folder 1237)
  - "Health in the United States, 1776-1978" and "Keystone Presentation" at the University of Colorado, October 4-5, 1978 (Box 112, Folder 1238)
  - Dr. John Knowles, August 7, 1969 (Box 112, Folder 1239)
  - "The National Health Problem" - GA Sound Filmstrip, 1971 (Box 113, Folder 1240)
  - Miscellaneous Certificates and Diplomas (Box 114, Folder 1241)
  - Rush University Diploma (Box 114, Folder 1242)
  - Pace University Diploma (Box 114, Folder 1243)
  - Massachusetts General Hospital (MGH) Treadwell Award (Box 114, Folder 1244)
  - Three Unidentified Tapes (Box 114, Folder 1245)
  - University of Maine Diplomas (Box 115, Folder 1246)
  - University of Maine Diplomas (Box 115, Folder 1247)
  - "Our Ailing Medical System" - "Fortune" Magazine, January 1970 (Box 115, Folder 1248)
  - Middlebury College Diploma (Box 115, Folder 1249)
  - Harvard Medical School Yearbook - "Aesculapiad", 1967 (Box 115, Folder 1250)
  - Plaque from Pace University (Box 115, Folder 1251)
  - Belmont Hill School Alumnus Award (Box 115, Folder 1252)
  - Framed Letter from Patricia Windrow Kline, [Date Created]June 30, 1973 (Box 115, Folder 1253)
  - Framed Watercolor and Pen of Maurice C. Pincoffs Lecturship Roster (Box 115, Folder 1254)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 115, Folder 1255)
    2 medals, Rockefeller Foundation identification card, American College of Physicians identification card.
    General note
    Housed in a microfilm box within box 115.
  - Microscope Slides (Box 116, Folder 1256)
  - Microscope Slides (Box 116, Folder 1257)
  - Plaque - American Arbitration Association (Box 117, Folder 1258)
  - Plaque - Massachusetts Junior Chamber of Commerce, [Date Created]1962 (Box 117, Folder 1259)
  - Plaque - Boston Junior Chamber of Commerce, [Date Created]1962 (Box 117, Folder 1260)
  - Plaque - Colgate-Diana Shore Winners Circle, [Date Created]1977 (Box 117, Folder 1261)
  - Plaque - Metropolitan Life Golden Anniversary - The Rockefeller Foundation, [Date Created]1974 (Box 117, Folder 1262)
  - Package (Box 118, Folder 1263)
    3 watercolor portraits of John H. Knowles; an aerial view of Boston.
- John H. Knowles photographs, 1944-1980; 1049
  Photographs
  - Portraits - Knowles, John (Box 35, Folder 357)
  - Knowles Family (Box 35, Folder 358)
  - Knowles - Associates (Box 35, Folder 359)
  - Work at Portsmouth Naval Hospital (Box 35, Folder 360)
  - MGH - Miscellaneous (Box 35, Folder 361)
  - Vietnam, 1967 (Box 36, Folder 362)
  - Illustrations - An analysis of the Pressure-Volume Characteristics of the Lung, 1961 (Box 36, Folder 363)
  - Illustrations for article "The Hospital" (Box 36, Folder 364)
  - Album "John H. Knowles, His RF Years" (Box 36, Folder 365)
  - Africa Trip, 1973 (Box 36, Folder 366)
  - Bellagio, 1973 June 9-12 (Box 36, Folder 367)
  - Bangkok Program Review, 1973 February (Box 36, Folder 368)
  - Hyderabad, India Trip, 1973 (Box 36, Folder 369)
  - CIAT Dedication - Cali, Colombia, 1973 (Box 36, Folder 370)
  - China Trip, 1975 (Box 36, Folder 371)
  - Family Planning Association Meeting - March 20-27, 1973 - St. Lucia (Box 36, Folder 372)
  - RF - Miscellaneous (Box 37, Folder 373)
  - Associates - Authors of "Doing Better and Feeling Worse" (Box 37, Folder 374)
  - Suffolk University, 1975 (Box 37, Folder 375)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 37, Folder 376)
  - John H. Knowles (Box 37, Folder 377)
  - Lantern Slides - Medical Research (Box L 44, Box L 45, Box L 46, Box L 47, Box L 48)
- Oversize, 1947-1975
  - Honorary degree to John Hilton Knowles: Doctor of Humane Letters, awarded by Boston University., AWARD (Quantity 1) (Folder 1)
  - "Why Shouldn't Blue Cross Pay Taxes?", 1964 May 15; POSTER (Quantity 1) (Folder 1)
    Separated Materials note
    removed from Series 2, Subseries 1, box 13, folders 150-154: reimbursements fro in-house patients
  - Series of 4 blueprints for the office of Dr. John H. Knowles., 1972 August-September; BLUEPRINT (Quantity 4) (Folder 1)
    Removed from box 84, folder 988
  - Series of 3 blueprint negatives for the proposed addition to the Vincent Burnum Building of the Massachusetts General Hospital., 1961 January 6; BLUEPRINT (Quantity 3) (Folder 1)
    removed from box 9, folder 96
  - Proposed alterations nursery fourth floor," Vincent Burnum Building, Massachusetts General Hospital., 1962 February 5; WHITEPRINT (Quantity 1) (Folder 1)
    removed from box 12, folder 143
  - Series of 2 whiteprints for the Mosley Building of the Massachusetts General Hospital., 1962; WHITEPRINT (Quantity 2) (Folder 1)
  - "Proposed alterations for psychiatric service," Bulfinch Building Mass.General Hospital, 1967 May 12; WHITEPRINT (Quantity 1) (Folder 1)
  - "Alterations to conference room," Vincent Burnum Building, Mass. General Hospital, 1965 April 13; WHITEPRINT (Quantity 1) (Folder 1)
  - Honorary degree: Doctor of Law, awarded by Suffolk University, 1975 June 8; AWARD (Quantity 1) (Folder 1)
    removed from Box 114
  - certificate of election as a Fellow of the New York Academy of Medicine, 1947 January 6; AWARD (Quantity 1) (Folder 1)
  - certificate of membership of the Medical Assistance Advisory Council, from the Commonwealth of Massachusetts (certificate and small program), 1966 December 13; AWARD (Quantity 2) (Folder 1)
  - honorary degree: Doctor of Science from the New York Medical College, 1975 June 3; AWARD (Quantity 2) (Folder 1)
  - license to practice medicine and surgery in New York State, 1972 May 15; AWARD (Folder 1)